Today's דף daf officially is 26, כ"ו. Kaf Vav. We will see
if we can get fully caught up. That's my goal. We pick
up, however, כ"א עמוד א Kaf Aleph Amud Aleph on the משנה.
Mishnah. So let's take a look. We had been dealing with the
theme of even if you're not supposed to marry, but if you
do, you don't have to divorce. We had a fascinating discussion about
conversion and suspected adultery.
And now we look at, we look at this next משנה Mishnah
within a
following a similar type of a theme. המביא גט, Hamavee get, משנה
Mishnah at the bottom of כ"א עמוד א. Kaf Aleph Amud Aleph.
המביא גט ממדינת הים. Hamavee get mimedinat hayam. So you think we
were in גיטין. Gittin. Somebody brings a גט get from overseas, which
is the first משנה Mishnah in גיטין. Gittin. And for anybody who's
learned that, what do you have to say when you bring a
גט get from overseas? Charlie, what do you have to say? בפני
נכתב ובפני נחתם. Bifnay nechtav u’bifnay nechtam. You have to testify that
it was signed and sealed correctly. So, let's say ואמר בפני נכתב
ובפני נחתם, v’amar bifnay nechtav u’bifnay nechtam, לא ישא את אשתו. lo
yisat et ishto. So the guy who came to testify that everything
was done correctly, he cannot marry the newly divorced woman. Okay. Raises
certain questions about his reliability and veracity. Now, let's say he says
הרגתי, haragtee, I killed the husband,
or הרגנו, haragnu, we killed the husband, לא ישא את אשתו, lo
yisat et ishto, don't marry the wife.
Now, of course,
what's bizarre here is that we're not at all problematizing the fact
that he just confessed to murder, but anyway, the point is that
he's testifying that the husband is dead in a quite drastic way,
and we also can't rely on that or let me rephrase this,
in order to rely on that, we cannot allow him to marry
the wife. If he marries the wife, it casts questions onto his
veracity. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, הרגתי לא תנשא אשתו, haragtee
lo tinasay ishto, I killed the husband, she cannot marry the wife,
הרגנו תנשא אשתו, haragnu tinasay ishto, we killed the husband, he can
marry the wife. Exactly what the difference is there, we will see
in the גמרא. Gemara. But this is other types of cases where
there are secondary concerns. I mean, we're really quite digressing, right? We
dealt with the case of two brothers or two people, I'm sorry,
two people, two sisters, marry, you know, אחות זקוקתו achot zekukato or
whatever it was, not אחות זקוקתו, achot z'kukato, well, I think it
was אחות זקוקתו Achot Zekukaso, etc., don't do יבום Yibum? with both
of them. And now we've gone into totally different areas about don't
marry, don't marry because of suspected adultery, don't marry because of a
suspected affair, don't marry because of the testimony about the suspected, well,
he actually confessed murder, but don't anyway marry because of the testimony
that allows the wife to remarry.
Does confession not have any weight?
Right. So that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say, which
is why the משנה Mishnah is not saying let's go ahead and
throw him in jail.
Maybe it was by accident?
Right. Well, it's not what it says. Okay.
Isn't it הרג? harag? Yeah. Okay, true.
It is true that להרוג leharog is to kill as opposed to
לרצוח, lirtzoach, which is to murder. Anyway, let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. טעמא דממדינת הים. Ta’ama d’mimedinat hayam.
The reason that he cannot marry the wife is because he's coming
from overseas. דעליה קסמכינן, De-alay kasamchinan,
because we're relying on his testimony. הא מארץ ישראל דלאו עליה קסמכינן,
Ha me’Eretz Yisrael d’lav alay kasamchinan, if he's delivering a גט get
and he's in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and he doesn't have to
testify that it was done correctly, but he still is the person
who's delivering it, and we're not relying on him, ישא את אשתו,
yisat et ishto, he can marry the wife. So the גמרא Gemara
says, one minute, והמת, v’hamet,
what about the case when he says he died, notice how the
גמרא Gemara reframed the idea that I killed him, when he says
the husband died, דלאו עליה קסמכינן, d’lav alay kasamchinan, we don't rely
on him. Now, that's crazy. What do you mean don't rely on
him? You're totally relying on him! He said he saw the husband
dead! No, because we have reframed what is the mechanics that's working
in that case. דאמר מר, De-amar mar, because we say, the master
teaches, אשה דייקא ומינסבא. isha dayka u’minsava. How can you rely on
one witness to remarry, one witness testifies the husband is dead? So
the גמרא Gemara really struggles with this and the answer the גמרא
Gemara gives is that the woman we trust the woman to investigate,
that since she knows that there are very, very harsh consequences if
it turns out the testimony was false and it turns out the
husband is alive and she remars, we trust her investigation that follows
the testimony that the husband is dead to be to totally ascertain
that it actually is correct. So this is a quite radical גמרא.
Gemara. It's not just somehow saying that that supports the testimony. In
the end, it's completely about her investigation that follows. So if that's
really true, then we're not really relying on him. דקתני לא ישא
את אשתו, de-katani lo yisat et ishto, so why can't he marry
the wife if we're not really relying on him in the case
where he testifies the husband is dead, we're really just relying on
the wife? So the גמרא Gemara says, no. התם ליכא כתבא הכא
איכא
כתבא. Hatam leka ksava, hacha ika ksava. There's still a big difference
between saying the husband is dead and just delivering a גט. get.
Saying the husband is dead, you still are testifying to some facts,
however much that's bolstered or, you know, maybe even the bulk of
it is done by the woman's investigation, you still are testifying to
facts and there's a need to, you know, not question the veracity.
Delivering a גט get without saying needing to say that it was
done
correctly. You can if you're delivering it in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
So that's the Gemara saying that's the difference.
כדתנן Kidnan like we taught in the mishna, מה בין גט למיתה,
Ma bein get lemita, what's the difference between divorce and death? Well
for the husband it's a big difference but anyway שהכתב מוכיח. She'haksav
mochiach. Okay,
that's the writ that proves that you are that this everything is
on the up and up, you have a signed document and as
long as it's in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael it doesn't need external
validation then the person is really doing nothing other than delivering as
opposed to testifying the husband is dead the guy is still doing
something.
Yeah maybe as asked before I came in is there an intrinsic
reliability on a document that comes from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael as
opposed to...
Yeah there's a general assumption that signed
documents the Gemara's phrase is עדים שבשטר כמי שנחקרה עדותן בבית דין.
Edis she'bishtar kemi she'nechkerah edusam be'veis din. If you have a signed
document even if it's not the signatures haven't been what we would
do is we would get them what's that called notarized which is
sort of what the בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם Bifnai nichtav u'bifnai nechtam
is doing but the Gemara says that על פי דין Al pi
din even without notarization two signatures on a document is like it's
completely been delivered in court and the testimony is accepted and it
sort of proves itself. So only when it comes from חוץ לארץ
Chutz la'aretz only if questions
about the reliability of the signatures I won't get into why but
anyway that's where it needs some external verification.
He needs the notary you don't need any of that.
We will worry about when we get to מסכת גיטין. Masechet Gittin.
Okay, מת הוא הרגנוהו לא ישא את אשתו. Mes hu haragnuhu lo
yisa es ishto.
So the Gemara says if you say however he died oh did
I leave out the word מת? Mes? I'm sorry. It didn't start
with I killed him. It started with he died. He died, I
killed him, we killed him, don't marry the wife. Again the common
denominator is the witness is testifying that the husband has died so
don't marry the wife because that will cast aspersions on the testimony.
So the Gemara says הוא ניהו דלא ישא את אשתו, Hu nihu
d'lo yisa es ishto, he cannot marry the wife, הא לאחר תינשא,
Ha l'acher tinase, she can marry a different woman... a different man.
Okay so therefore even if he says I murdered the husband the
only problem basically it's acceptable testimony. The point is that what's clear
in the mishna is it's acceptable testimony that the husband is dead.
The only problem is don't marry the wife because that will then
cast questions on the testimony. But saying that you murdered the husband
we're still allowed to extract from that the fact that the husband
is dead like any normal עד אחד Ed echad right? People know
this halacha this is going to be a major part of יבמות
Yevamos that even even though we always need שני עדים Shenai edim
when it's a question about a husband dying in order that the
woman should not be left עגונה Agunah we actually allow to rely
on a single testify witness not even not only a single it
doesn't matter man or woman free person or slave very even hearsay
testimony to testify to the fact that the husband is dead. So
what the Gemara's saying is okay so the problem is don't you
can't he can't marry because that will undermine the testimony but clearly
the testimony is acceptable. Somebody says I murdered the husband we extract
from that that the husband is dead and the woman can be
remarried. Yes?
So if someone's testifying to his brother's death to get him out
of having to do יבום? Yibum.
Meaning
does that free... yeah I think so. Does that free the woman
from would that be yeah presumably yes.
Well he would be freed he's obligated to...
obligated to do יבום. Yibum Right sorry good point.
Obligated to do
יבום Yibum right right right right right right right it would have
to be testifying that the that the brother-in-law is dead and then
it frees the woman to marry some anyway right.
Does that outweigh the who does that outweigh the fact that he's
still being a witness in his brother's death... the guy's death to
die? Like...
No but they're pointing out that that's the opposite of what you're
saying it's not what do you mean? What do you mean? What's
he saying?
The fact that he has an obligation to do יבום Yibum is
stronger than the fact that like he's in he's involved he could
be...
Apply יבום yibum to this case in the mishna right? Anyone that
gave the testimony that I killed him. So the mishna says I'm
not allowed to marry her it undermines the...
oh I understand.
But what if it's my brother?
That's a good
presumably he'd have to do חליצה. Chalitzah. It's a good question. Try
to actually tie this mishna into our מסכת. Maseches. Okay good point.
If he's the brother then presumably he'd have to do חליצה. Chalitzah.
Okay let's take a
look let's take a look at the Gemara.
Okay הוא ניהו דלא ישא את אשתו הא לאחר תינשא Hu nihu
d'lo yisa es ishto ha l'acher tinase she can marry another man.
והאמר רב יוסף, Ve'ha'amar Rav Yosef, Rav Yosef says if somebody comes
and testifies פלוני רבעני לרצוני Ploni revani lirtzoni a certain man a
man testifies that another man what did I skip a line? לאונסי?
Le'onsi?
I said לאונסי. Le'onsi. Another man another man had sex with me
against my will so he's basically testifying look this is obviously these
are Gemaras obviously very hard to read in the contemporary whatever in
our search whatever given the
given the contemporary attitudes towards gay men and women but the Gemara
is clearly dealing with it through a biblical perspective and this is
you know... This is a חיוב מיתה, Hiyuv Misa, this act, and
therefore the question is somebody who goes ahead and testifies to it.
So if he says it was against my will, so he's not
saying that he himself did a sin, he was forced, okay, he
was raped by another man. So, but he's testifying that the other
man did this act, did this act.
So הוא ואחר מצטרפים להרגו. Hu ve'acher mitztarfim lehargo. He and another
person can come joint witnesses to testify against this man and
for the to execute him in the court for this act. Okay,
so therefore, even though he was involved, if it was against his
will, if he was raped, he does not get excluded. However, if
he says ברצוני, Birtzoni, it was done willingly, I did it willingly,
I was a willing participant, then רשע הוא, Rasha hu, he's saying
that he himself was sinning, and therefore he's a רשע, rasha, and
the תורה Torah says אל תשת ידך עם רשע להיות עד חמס.
Al tashet yadcha im rasha liheyot ed chamas. He can't combine with
another person to testify. He's excluded himself from testimony because he said
he was a willing participant. So the relevant point about this is
and this is a סוגיא sugya of
פלגינן דיבורא. Palginan dibura. Can we split his words? Take the part
of the testimony that is not about himself and and still use
it. So here we see we can't. If he testifies that he
was involved in an act, we cannot say well, okay, you can't
testify against yourself, but we're going to bracket that and only focus
on the part of the testimony that applies to somebody else. No,
you in the process have testified that you're that you're an invalid
witness, that you've done the sin and therefore it invalidates you as
a witness, so we have to throw the whole testimony out. So
that's true in that case, it should be true in this case.
Somebody basically testifies he murdered the husband. Okay, you're basically according to
you, you're an invalid witness, we can't accept the testimony. So the
גמרא Gemara now, now the obvious answer would be that's the first
case is to prosecute somebody in court, right, in order to apply
the death penalty. There maybe we have very exacting standards. Here we're
dealing with testifying the husband is dead, right, as we're telling you,
even one witness, we don't distinguish man or woman, free person or
slave, so there maybe we are willing to do a פלגינן דיבורא
Palginan dibura and extract the relevant data and bracket the question
of the fact that according to your own testimony you're a murderer.
Yes, David.
I'm assuming is this in the context of a בריסק Brisk style
of conceptualization? Is that
the case or is that splitting something that came before his analysis?
This idea that you just described about פלגינן
דיבורא, Palginan dibura, that's not related to the whole בריסקר Brisker approach.
That's already straight in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, and it doesn't sort
of work it's not like directly about the type of categories that
they בריסק Brisk has created. וכי תימא, Vechi teima, yeah, שאני עדות
אשה דהקילו בה רבנן, Shani edut isha dehikilu ba rabanan, so the
גמרא Gemara says that alright, maybe this testimony about the wife, and
therefore the rabbis are lenient about it. Okay. ואמר רב מנשיא, Ve'amar
Rav Menashia, and רב מנשיא Rav Menashia says, גזלן דדבריהם כשר
לעדות אשה.
Gazlan dedivreihem
kasher le'edut isha. A rabbinic גזלן gazlan like gamblers let's say that
are rabbinically invalid as witnesses, they can testify relating to the wife.
Okay. However, גזלן דדברי תורה פסול לעדות אשה. Gazlan dedivrei Torah pasul
le'edut isha.
So a biblical somebody who is a although again we have a
wide range of witnesses that are accepted, not somebody who is biblically
invalid. Now again it's interesting, a woman is biblically invalid, but this
person is biblically invalid for purposes for reasons of like some type
of sin and transgression. So that person is invalid. Now of course
you could also make a distinction which תוספות Tosafot raises. If somebody
there are two types of ways of invalidating a witness. One is
because of a sin relating to money where basically the point is
he's basically telling you he'll sin for money so basically he's telling
you his testimony can be bought. Okay? So that type of a
person you understand why you don't want to testify about the woman's
dead husband because basically you're afraid that his testimony could be bought.
There's another type of a person that's invalid because they're just סתם
stam a sinner, they eat they eat חזיר, chazir, נבילה לתיאבון, neveila
leteiavon, okay?
So why is that type of a person necessarily invalid for עדות
אשה? edut isha? Not as obvious. Alright, so תוספות Tosafot anyway raises
that question. The גמרא Gemara here does not distinguish. So it says
according to this person's testimony he's a murderer, alright, and therefore how
could you accept him for עדות אשה? edut isha? Again there you
could still distinguish that maybe only somebody who's biblically invalid because of
external testimony not because of a person's own confession. Alright, but this
is still what the גמרא Gemara is bothered. By his own confession
he's a murderer, he should be invalid for this testimony. So the
גמרא Gemara says נימא רב מנשיא דאמר כרבי יהודה. Nema Rav Menashia
de'amar k'Rabbi Yehuda.
Maybe רב מנשיא Rav Menashia says like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. One
minute, ah because רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda in the משנה mishna says
that if he says I'm the murderer we don't accept the testimony.
So maybe that רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, the other way of saying
it is that the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma rejects this and allows
a biblically invalid witness to be a witness. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, אמר לך רב מנשיא, Amar lach Rav Menashia, רב מנשיא
Rav Menashia would say אמרי לה רב מנשיא, Amre leh Rav Menashya,
רב מנשיא Rav Menashya say, "אנא דאמרי אפילו רבנן," Ana de'amri afilu
Rabbanon, even the Rabbis who accept the guy who says he's a
murderer, my position works with them. טעמא דרבנן הכא כדרבא, Ta'ama de-Rabbanon
hacha kiderava, it's like רבא, Rava, דאמר רבא, de-amar Rava, רבא Rava
says, "אדם קרוב אצל עצמו, adam karov etzel atzmo, ואין אדם משים
עצמו רשע." ve-ein adam mesim atzmo rasha. A person is close to
himself, he's, you know, he's his own best relative, his own closest
relative, and therefore he does not make himself into a רשע, rasha,
which is basically a way of saying פלגינן דיבורא, palginan diburei, that
we do split his testimony, and therefore we say the testimony that
relates to you yourself we throw it out, because you're now not
allowed to testify against yourself, okay. You can, the only time you
can testify against yourself, right, confession doesn't work in הלכה. halacha. It
only works in monetary areas. You can admit to a debt, you
can admit to a monetary obligation, but if you admit to a
crime that is not acceptable, you know, which is about מיתה misa
or מלקות malkos or whatever, that is completely irrelevant. We need external
testimony. So therefore the part that you testified against yourself that you're
a murderer is irrelevant and we throw it out, and we only
accept the part that the guy is actually dead. Of course, why
don't we say that about the other case in the גמרא, Gemara,
where the גמרא Gemara starts with, right, about the case of rape
and so on? So take a look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi
says like this, אמר, amar,
רש"י Rashi says like this, oh you know what, let's not do
רש"י, Rashi, let's continue the גמרא Gemara because the גמרא Gemara self-clarifies.
לימא רב יוסף דאמר כרבי יהודה? Leima Rav Yosef de-amar kederabbi Yehuda?
שהרי רב יוסף, She-harei Rav Yosef, רב יוסף Rav Yosef is the
one that spoke about the case of rape and he says that
you don't split the words, that you only take the part that
you have to throw out the whole testimony, and we're saying basically
you split the words. So maybe רב יוסף Rav Yosef has to
go like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you don't accept the testimony
when he says "I'm a murderer." So אמר לך רב יוסף, Amar
lach Rav Yosef, no, אנא דאמרי אפילו רבנן, ana de-amri afilu Rabbanon,
again, I can work with the רבנן. Rabbanon. So again, how is
this different, right? So the גמרא Gemara says, ושאני עדות אשה דאקילו
בה רבנן. ve-shani edus isha de-akilu bah Rabbanon. Okay, and but we're
more lenient here because it's testimony about the woman getting remarried, so
we don't have the normal same standard where I'm saying that you
would throw out the whole testimony. ורב מנשיא דאמר כרבי יהודה, Ve-Rav
Menashya de-amar kederabbi Yehuda, but it's רב מנשיא Rav Menashya who says
like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Okay, because רב מנשיא Rav Menashya is
the one that says that biblically you throw it out, so even
by עדות אשה edus isha I wouldn't say that I would say
by עדות אשה edus isha you accept it. So it's interesting is
that the גמרא Gemara sort of takes two halves of the answer
and it could have combined the answer. What it basically says is
the following. רב מנשיא Rav Menashya who says that we throw out
biblically invalid testimony for עדות אשה edus isha or biblically invalid witnesses
for עדות אשה edus isha would basically say, I don't agree with
רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, I say we split if somebody testifies against
themselves we only take the relevant part about the other person not
about themselves. So I disagree with רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, and therefore
in this case we can take the testimony about the husband even
though I would say that you know normally you have to throw
out a biblically invalid witness for עדות אשה. edus isha. רב יוסף
Rav Yosef who says we don't split the testimony would say, I
don't agree with רב מנשיא, Rav Menashya, I think that even a
biblically invalid witness can work for עדות אשה, edus isha, and therefore
even a guy who says he's a murderer we can accept it
for עדות אשה. edus isha. Of course, he could have had something
that says everybody agrees, everybody agrees that when you combine the two
factors, number one, it's only עדות אשה, edus isha, and number two,
we have the possibility of splitting the words, in that case scenario
we'll do that. You might hold that when it's only one of
those it's not acceptable, but when those two are combined we actually
will. So that's the case in the משנה. Mishnah. According to the
תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, even if he says "I am the murderer,"
we accept it. Why? Wouldn't we normally throw something like that out?
So either because no, in a case of testimony about a husband
we won't throw it out, or because no, we won't throw those
things out because we'll split the words. Or what I'm saying is
let's say both, because it's a case about the woman remarrying, that
will allow us to split the words and only accept the relevant
part of the testimony not the irrelevant part that he's the murderer,
yes.
So your understanding is saying that if he's a biblically invalid witness,
splitting your words means we're basically saying you're a valid witness? Correct.
But it's semantics.
No it isn't. We will not accept a biblically invalid witness when
we have it due to external testimony, but we will accept it
but if it's due to your own testimony then we don't believe
then we don't accept the fact that you're an invalid witness, okay.
Or right, so that's the difference.
And then if he says "I am שליח בית דין," shliach beis
din, so then that would be okay to marry him, right? Like
in other words he was committed in a capital court and I
killed him?
Yeah, yeah, yeah. So that's not even the issue.
Because he killed him himself so to speak?
Yeah, yeah, that's what Michael's saying. Then that's not an issue at
all. That's not an issue at all. That doesn't raise his status
as a רשע. rasha. Okay, so okay. הרגתיב הרגנוהו תנשא. Haragtiv haragnuhu
tinasei. מאי שנא הרגתיב ומאי שנא הרגנוהו? Mai shna haragtiv u-mai shna
haragnuhu? So we sort of pointed out that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
in the משנה Mishnah who makes a distinction is bothered by not
accepting the testimony when he says that he himself that he himself
is a רשע. rasha. Okay. So then what's the difference if he
says "I murdered him" or "we murdered him"? Even if it's a
"we murdered him," you're still a רשע, rasha, you were part of
a murder. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב יהודה באומר אני
הייתי עם הורגיו. Amar Rav Yehuda be-omer ani hayisi im horgov. It
doesn't mean "I murdered him." It means "I was part I was
there, I was part of the group, I was part of the
planning, I drove the getaway car," okay, but I didn't actually murder
him. So the גמרא Gemara says... והתניא אמרו לו לרב יהודה מעשה
בלסטיס Ve'hatanya amru lo leRav Yehuda ma'aseh belistis or לסטים listim we
pronounce it but
I know, but it's really לסטיס, listis, it's really the singular, אחד.
echad.
Anyway, story with a certain bandit שיצא ליהרג במגיזת קפוטקיה. sheyatza lehayeireig
bemgizat Kapotkia.
He was going out to be killed in this place, meaning presumably
by the court, ואמר להם לכו אמרו לה לאשת שמעון בן כהן,
ve'amar lahem lechu imru la le'ishet Shimon ben Kohen, go tell the
wife of שמעון בן כהן, Shimon ben Kohen, אני הרגתי את בעלה,
ani haragti et ba'alah,
that I murdered. So here it was, it was like a confession
he makes right before he's executed. Go let the wife know of
שמעון בן כהן, Shimon ben Kohen, I killed her husband. He's worried
about trying to make up, you know, make some amends right before
he dies, בכניסתי ללוד bechnisati leLud
when I was going into לוד. Lud. ואמרו לה בכניסתו ללוד ve'amru
la bechnisato leLud or when he was going into לוד. Lud. והשיאו
את אשתו vehisiyu et ishto and they married off his wife. So
here you see that the guy is ממש, mamash, he's a murderer,
and we still accept the testimony. And this is not just his
own saying he's a murderer, he's being taken out to be executed,
okay?
So the גמרא Gemara says,
so anyway, so they said this to רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, "Don't
you see that somebody can, what do you call it, that we
can accept the testimony of somebody even if he says he's a
murderer?" So he says, משם ראיה? misham raya? אמר להם משם ראיה?
amar lahem misham raya? You want to bring a proof from that?
באומר אני הייתי עם הורגיו. be'omer ani hayiti im horgav. He wasn't
saying that he was the murderer. He was saying, "I was there,
I was part of the group," but not that I literally did
it myself. So you see, so you see that רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda says, yeah, so you see that רב יהודה Rav Yehuda though
says that the case that רב יהודה Rav Yehuda accepts is when
he says he was part of the group and not when he
did it himself. So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute, ולסטיס קתני.
velistis katani.
It says that he was a bandit. שנתפס על ידי לסטיות. shenitpas
al yedei listiyut. So fine, he was captured for banditry, but that
doesn't necessarily prove that he was a murderer. It says, והיוצא ליהרג
קתני, vehayotzei lehayeireig katani, he's going to be executed. So clearly he's
a murderer. So how could anybody accept the testimony? So the גמרא
Gemara says, no, בדינא דאומות העולם דלא דייקי וקטלי. bedina de'umot ha'olam
dlo dayki vekatli.
That's the non-Jewish court that they don't necessarily have sufficient evidence, they'll
just kill based on types of suspicions, okay? But אין הכי נמי,
ein hachi nami, everybody would agree that if he was a convicted
murderer by a בית דין, Beit Din, we couldn't accept the testimony,
at least according to what we said before about רב מנשה, Rav
Menashe, that we don't accept testimony of, you know, of רשעים, resha'im,
of biblically invalid witnesses even for the testimony of the husband. Okay,
רב מנשה Rav Menashe might argue, you know, others might argue on
that, say we accept everybody for witness of the husband. But the
גמרא's Gemara saying is both תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda assume that if he's clearly a רשע, rasha, clearly a
murderer, we don't accept the testimony. ותנא קמא VeTanna Kamma says, so
if he testifies against himself it's irrelevant. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says,
no, if he testifies against himself it is relevant, we don't accept
the testimony, but we'll accept it if he says he was part
of the group even if he wasn't actually, as long as he
wasn't actually the murderer himself. Yeah.
But he's being executed though, not על פי al pi his own
testimony against himself.
No,
I don't, who knows, maybe he is, but it's being done by
the non-Jewish court, so it's not relevant, it's not sufficient evidence for
us to הלכתית halachitit define him as a murderer, yes.
Unless he like is like a, not like, like, you know, his
mental health, if he's condemning himself to like imprisonment or death, can't
you say that, oh, so he probably, if he said it he
probably did it if he's going to get this punishment? Is there
no legitimacy to that logic?
Well, first of all, the רמב"ם Rambam says that the reason you
don't accept confessions is because you might assume that people confess for
a whole wide range of reasons, not necessarily because they've done it,
and maybe because they're also not so mentally well and whatever, and
other possible reasons, right? And so,
but anyway, but the point is that what you're saying is exactly
what the conclusion is according to the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. You
extract the facts without necessarily condemning him as the one who did
it. Yeah, so that is what the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says.
All right, so let's take a look at the משנה. Mishnah. חכם
שאסר את האישה. Chacham she'asar et ha'ishah.
So that was interesting because those were cases where you're not supposed
to marry, but of course the hanging question is because the theme
here is reasons not to marry and if you do marry do
you have to then get divorced? So what that משנה Mishnah was
lacking was the final line. What happens if the guy who delivered
the גט get or the guy who said the husband is dead
did marry the woman? What do we do then? Okay, so that'll
come up in the גמרא, Gemara, but that obviously is the theme
here and it's funny that it didn't end with that and now
we get to another case of not supposed to marry. חכם שאסר
את האישה בנדר על בעלה. Chacham she'asar et ha'ishah bineder al ba'alah.
So basically a woman came to a חכם Chacham and said, "I
just made this vow and my husband is telling me that if
I can't get it annulled he's going to divorce me." And the,
or maybe he didn't say that, but okay, anyway, and the חכם
Chacham says, looks at it, says, "No, I'm sorry, there's no way
we can annul the vow. There's not a, there's not any opening
here." Okay, so then the woman gets divorced and then the חכם
Chacham basically goes ahead and proposes marriage to the woman. Okay, so
that you're not supposed to do that, okay? חכם שאסר את האישה
בנדר על בעלה Chacham she'asar et ha'ishah bineder al ba'alah
based on his vow, she became forbidden to her husband. It's actually
even worse than I said, okay, because I said that her husband
said he was going to divorce her. Here it says that the
נדר neder actually forbids her to her husband, so basically she made
herself, like she basically said, you know, she said "I am forbidden
to my husband." for like sex with me is forbidden on my
husband which you can sort of do with a נדר. neder. So
really the result is that it's impossible for she and her husband
to continue living together. So it's even a more extreme case.
הרי זה לא ישאנה.
Harei zeh lo yisaena. He can't marry her after they get divorced.
מיאנה או שחלצה בפניו.
Miena o shechaltsa b'fanav.
Now let's say he was involved in another thing that got a
woman separated from her husband or the man she was connected to.
Basically he was part of the בית דין beis din that supervised
he was a minor that was married to this guy through the
brothers and mother, so she had the right of verbal refusal, מיאון.
miun. But you need that in front of a בית דין. beis
din. He was part of that בית דין. beis din. Or she
did חליצה chalitsa to her brother-in-law and he was part of the
בית דין beis din that observed that. So in that case ישאנה,
yisaena, that case he can marry her afterwards. מפני שהוא בית דין
mipnei she'hu beis din because it wasn't him himself, he was part
of a בית דין beis din and therefore we won't necessarily impugn
him, there were two other people that were there as well. Of
course the other thing you could say is that those are cases
that don't require the same degree of discretion. Right, the case about
נדר neder requires a lot of discretion. Now everything requires some discretion.
Are you going to invalidate the חליצה, chalitsa, invalidate the מיאון? miun?
There's a technical problem or whatever, but not the same degree. But
the משנה mishnah doesn't focus on that, it focuses on the fact
that it was not him acting alone. Of course, whatever, I think
they've done these sociological studies, I'm sure Charlie could tell us all
about that, and where they in like between the ways that group
operates and individuals operate and anyway, basically somebody who knows what he's
doing can manipulate a group to come to a decision himself and
in certain ways even hide the fact that he's responsible for it.
Solomon. What? Right. Anyway, but okay, the משנה mishnah is saying either
there's less to genuinely be concerned about or less to be concerned
about in terms of appearances. Okay, so the גמרא gemara says like
this: הא התירו ישאנה. ha hitira yisaena. So from the משנה mishnah
we see that if the חכם chacham actually freed her from the
from the נדר neder and then the husband dies or divorces her
for some other reason, he can marry her, which makes sense. Okay,
so במאי עסקינן? b'mai askinan? So what's the case? אילימא בחד, ileima
b'chad, if it's a single person annulling the vow. חד מי מצי
מתיר? chad mi matsi matir? How can a single חכם chacham release
somebody from their vow? והא אמר, ve'ha amar, don't we say either
רב אמר רבי חייא Rav amar Rabbi Chiya or רב אמר רבי
חייא בר אבין אמר רב עמרם, Rav amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abin
amar Rav Amram, תנא התרת נדרים בשלושה. tana hataras nedarim b'shlosha. You
need a בית דין beis din for התרת נדרים hataras nedarim as
we all know on ערב ראש השנה. erev Rosh Hashanah. ואלא בשלושה?
ve'ella b'shlosha? Okay, fine, it was part of a בית דין. beis
din. סו מי חשידי? so mi chashidi? So if you have three
people doing it, why would any one of them be suspect? You're
not operating on your own. והתנן, ve'hasnan, the end of the משנה
mishnah says מיאנה או שחלצה בפניו ישאנה מפני שהוא בית דין. miena
o shechaltsa b'fanav yisaena mipnei she'hu beis din. That if it's part
of an act of בית דין, beis din, then you can marry
afterwards. So the גמרא gemara says לעולם בחד. le'olam b'chad. We are
dealing with a case of one. וכדאמר רב חסדא אמר רבי יוחנן
ביחיד מומחה. uch'de'amar Rav Chisda amar Rabbi Yochanan b'yachid mumcheh. That actually,
even though we need three for a התרת נדרים, hataras nedarim, you
can also do it with a single person if he is an
expert, if he's a מומחה. mumcheh. What exactly qualifies מומחה mumcheh I'm
not going to go into, but you can have somebody who's a
real expert. Three people who are laypeople can do it, one person
who's an expert. הכא נמי ביחיד מומחה. hacha nami b'yachid mumcheh. So
that's the case here. So yes, the case in the משנה mishnah
is where it is a single חכם chacham who is doing it.
Again, you could also suggest the difference of degree of discretion, but
that is not where the גמרא gemara is going. מיאנה או שחלצה,
miena o shechaltsa, but if it's part of a בית דין beis
din he can, one of the members of the בית דין beis
din can marry the woman. טעמא דבית דין. taama d'beis din. Reason
is בית דין. beis din. הא בתרי לא. ha bitrei lo. Let's
say it was a case that you needed two people. So then
maybe since he's a 50 percent of the vote, maybe in that
case he cannot marry the woman. Now what would be a case
of two? So מיתיבי מהא דתנן, meisheiv mehade itnan, well let's take
a look. Case in
a משנה, mishnah, actually דתניא, d'tanya, ברייתא. braisa. אין הם מעידים חתומים
על שדי מקח. ein hem me'idim chasamim al sdei mekach. You have
two witnesses on a field of a on a sale document that
something was sold. ועל גט אשה, ve'al get ishah, or on a
woman's writ of divorce. לא חשו חכמים לדבר זה. lo chashu chachamim
l'davar zeh. The sages were not concerned. What were they concerned about?
Can one of the witnesses of the גט get remarry the wife?
Can one of the witnesses on a sale of a field go
ahead and purchase the field? So there you could say, maybe the
גט get is a forgery and you're doing it so you can
remarry the wife. Or the writ of sale is a forgery and
you're doing it so that you can the field can sell it
to a third party who who's agreed on this whole scheme and
will sell you the field. No, we're not concerned. So you see
even when there are just two, anytime you're not operating alone, we're
not concerned. So the גמרא gemara says, so what is it? Do
you need two or do you need three? So the גמרא gemara
says, no, היא גופא קא משמע לן. hi gufa k'mashma lan. לאפוקי
ממאן דאמר מיאון בפני שנים, l'afukei mi'man d'amar miun bifnei shnayim, קא
משמע לן מיאון בג'. k'mashma lan miun b'gimmel. The גמרא gemara is
saying you're right, that the משנה mishnah is בית דין beis din
is not needed, really anything more than one. In passing, it's pointing
out that it is a בית דין, beis din, don't think that
מיאון miun only requires two, מיאון miun requires three, it does require
a בית דין. beis din. But in the end of the day,
it doesn't need a בית דין beis din to allow remarriage. Even
two, as long as you're not
acting independently, remarriage would be allowed. Okay. איבעיא
להו. iba'i lehu. So now they raise the question. כנס מה שיוציא.
kanas mah she'yotsi. Finally, that seems to be the reason these משניות
mishnayos were here, but we didn't tell the end line. All these
cases of not remarrying in the case of the חכם Chocham with
the נדר, Neder, or in the case of the בפני נכתב Befonei
nechtov or the husband is dead, what happens if they got married?
Can you remarry? Now רש"י Rashi says it's talking about if you
look at the רש"י, Rashi, חכם ומביא גט קאי. Chocham u'meivi get
kai.
It's talking about
both of the earlier cases. Okay, about the case of the חכם
Chocham and the נדר Neder and the guy bringing the גט. Get.
If you look at the little א Alef in the הגר"א, Grah,
he says וכן כתב הרמב"ם והשולחן ערוך, Vechen kasav HaRambam veHaShulchan Aruch,
אבל רשב"א כתב דלא קאי רק אמתניתין זו אחרונה, Aval Rashba kasav
d'lo kai rak amasnishin zu achrona,
but not on the case of מביא גט. meivi get. So there's
some question which is the scope of the גמרא'ס Gemara's question of
what's the בדיעבד Bedi'eved story, just on this משנה Mishna or on
the previous two משניות. Mishnayos. Anyway, let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says, okay, what's happen if they actually got married? So רב כהנא
אמר כנס מוציא, Rav Kahana amar knas motzi, you have to divorce.
רב אשי אמר כנס אינו מוציא, Rav Ashi amar knas eino motzi,
you don't divorce. Of course the, you know, it seems that the
sense of these משניות Mishnayos is don't divorce, it only mentioned one
case so far, the case of adultery, right, which was very weighty,
which it was a divorce. But anyway here's a debate in these
un, you know, in these cases where it's not spelled out. So
תני ליה רב זוטא בדבי רב פפא כדברי אומר כנס אינו מוציא.
Tani lei Rav Zuti bidvei Rav Papa kidvrei omer knas eino motzi.
So רב זוטא Rav Zuti taught a ברייתא Braisa
whatever according to the position that if married you did not have
to divorce, you do not have to divorce. אמרו ליה רבנן לרב
אשי, Amru lei Rabbanan le-Rav Ashi, so the rabbis said to רב
אשי, Rav Ashi, so גמרא או סברא? Gemara o sevara?
So
when you know, this teaching that you רב אשי Rav Ashi say,
which was רב אשי'ס Rav Ashi's position? Oh, he does not have
to divorce. Is that a tradition that you have or is that
logical? Is that something that you've derived logically? אמר להו מתניתין היא,
Amar le-hu masnisin hee, which is sort of like neither. Okay, but
I can figure it out from the משנה, Mishna, maybe that's סברא
sevara to infer from a משנה. Mishna. Anyway, הניסת משפחה ונשתחררה מעובדת
כוכבים ונתגיירה הרי זה לא יכנוס ואם כנס אינו מוציא. Hanissas meshifcha
venishtachrera me'ovedes kochavim venisgayera harei zeh lo yichnos ve-im knas eino motzi.
So
you see these other cases, right? The one exception was adultery, but
these cases about not marrying because of a conversion or whatever, things
that you were suspected of an affair, בדיעבד bedi'eved if you get
married you do not have to divorce. אלמא, Alma, you see, ברננה
לא מפקינן. birnana lo mafkinan. Just because of rumor and a concern
oh people are going to say whatever, the rumor's true etc., we're
not going to
to divorce as a based on those concerns. הכא נמי ברננה לא
מפקינן. Hacha nami birnana lo mafkinan. Here too we're not going to
do it based on those concerns of rumor. Now you can understand,
right, why these cases are not exactly the same. It's one thing
the guy marries the woman he was suspected of having an affair
with, right, who was a non-Jewish woman or whatever. What's the result
of the fact if the rumor were true? If the rumor were
true, he did something wrong and whatever, people think he did something
wrong. Okay. Here, if the rumor were true, what's the rumor? Maybe
the husband isn't dead, maybe the גט get isn't valid. So this
woman, you know, is an אשת איש. eishes ish. Okay, that's a
pretty serious concern. Now, now you understand why the רשב"א Rashba said
that this was only going on the case of the נדר, neder,
right? Because the case of the נדר, neder, even if the חכם
chocham manipulated it, the woman is still legitimately divorced. The husband still
gave a גט get to the wife,
right? So their case maybe at most it's a concern of rumor.
But in the case where the guy brought the גט get or
the guy testified the husband has died, you do not want there
to be doubts about whether the woman is legitimately divorced or widowed.
So you could really make a big difference between those cases. Yes,
Joe?
I'm interested in גמרא או סברא. Gemara o sevara. Is citing of
a משנה mishna the same as גמרא? Gemara?
No, I thought it was the same as סברא. sevara.
So is גמרא Gemara potentially like פסוקים? Pesukim?
No,
גמרא Gemara is like an oral tradition, you know, it's more like
the הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai category.
So it wouldn't be משנה mishna then that's a third?
No, I don't know, no, I mean משנה mishna might be a
third answer, right? It's not just logic but I think it's primarily
in the סברא sevara answer. I think it's primarily the סברא sevara
answer.
Yeah. Alright, next משנה: mishna: וכולם שהיו להם נשים ומתו מותרות להינשא
להם. Vekulam shehoyu lahem nashim umesu mutaros lehinasay lahem. So now this
משנה mishna finally does not deal with if they married do they
have to divorce, but it's a qualifying again
when are we concerned that these people might be lying. So all
these people, the חכם chocham who was not able to release the
woman from the vow, or the guy who brought the גט, get,
and all these or the guy who said the husband died, he
killed him. If they were actually married at the time and then
when they, you know, delivered the גט get or when he said
you don't have to, you know, I can't release you from your
vow, and then their wives died, so מותרות להינשא להם, mutaros lehinasay
lahem, then they can get married, which is fascinating. So even in
a polygamous society, okay, where you know, polygamy is allowed, it was
really a rarity, certainly in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael it was a
rarity, and therefore, and anyway when it was done mostly it was
only done by very wealthy men who could support multiple wives. So
therefore the משנה mishna is basically assuming that at a practical level
if a man is already married he's not going to marry another
woman. Okay, which is just fascinating, right? Because הלכה halacha allows it
but the משנה mishna takes it for granted that that basically won't
happen. Therefore, if they're already married, we do not have to suspect
that they are manipulating everything, and then what? And then waiting for
their wives to
die? So now of course it is funny because you could say
they're manipulating and they're planning on divorcing their wives, which could be
done unilaterally, okay? But interestingly, we're not concerned about that. If they're
already married, we're not concerned that they were manipulating.
Okay, וכולן שנישאו לאחרים ונתגרשו או שנתאלמנו מותרות להינשא להם. Ve-khulan she-nis'u
le-acherim ve-nisgarshu o she-nisalmenu mutaros le-hinase lahem. Also, if there is a
somebody who interrupts, we had this idea before about the case of
the conversion and so on. If they went ahead and the woman
that you brought a גט get and said that this woman was
divorced, you know, בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם Bifnai nechtav u-vifnai nechtam or
that the husband had died, and this woman married somebody else, and
then the second guy she married died or divorced her, then you
can marry her. Because since you're not marrying her immediately
afterwards, nobody's going to say, 'Oh, you faked the whole thing so
she could marry another man so then she could marry you.' Right?
If you really were interested in this woman, you would not have
wanted her to go ahead and marry another man.
She's right, she refused!
All right, maybe. Anyway, we don't have those suspicions if she married
another guy in between.
וכולן מותרות לבניהם או לאחיהם. Ve-khulan mutaros li-vneihem o le-acheihem. Interestingly also,
all of these, the חכם chacham and the guy who brings the
גט get can marry—I'm sorry, not the חכם, chacham, the women, all
these women can marry the brothers or the sons of the people
that have caused—that have allowed them to be divorced from their husband,
right? So the guy bringing a גט, get, he can't marry this
woman, but the woman can marry his brother or his son. We
don't assume that he is manipulating and lying and falsifying for the
sake that a relative of his could marry this woman. All right?
Which is interesting, you know, sometimes people do favors for their relatives.
Okay, but that we're not afraid of. So we're limiting the level
of our concern. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. מתו
אין נתגרשו לא. Mesu in, nisgarshu lo. Right, so importantly, this was
the point I raised: maybe the guy's already married, but he's planning
on divorcing his wife, and which he can do unilaterally. So the
גמרא Gemara says actually that's a good point from the משנה. Mishnah.
The משנה Mishnah only says that if he's married and his wife
dies, then he can marry the woman. But if he's married and
he divorces his wife, he can't marry the woman, because then we
could say
he had it all planned. He was going to get this woman,
fake a גט, get, divorce his wife, and then marry her. And
it's even better that way because it looks more כשר kosher because
when he gave the גט, get, he was still married. So the
גמרא Gemara says, so מתו אין נתגרשו לא, Mesu in, nisgarshu lo,
if they divorce their wives they cannot remarry this woman or marry
this woman. So אמר ליה רב הלל לרב אשי, Amar lei Rav
Hillel le-Rav Ashi, wait a minute, we have a ברייתא baraisa that
says, אפילו נתגרשו, Afilu nisgarshu, that even if they divorce their wives,
they... אפילו נתגרשו, Afilu nisgarshu, excuse me, אפילו נתגרשו, Afilu nisgarshu, even
if they divorce their wives, they can then go ahead and marry
this woman. It's okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, לא קשיא, Lo
kashya, it's not difficult. הא דהוי קטטה הא דלא הוי קטטה. Ha
de-havi ketata, ha de-la havi ketata. Was there—were they already fighting with
their wives or not?
Now, which way does it go? So look at רש״י. Rashi. רש״י
Rashi said what to me, I was assuming the opposite. Take a
look at רש״י, Rashi, he says, הא, Ha, three lines into the
גמרא Gemara in
רש״י, Rashi, הא דקתני אפילו נתגרשו כגון דהוה להו קטטה. Ha de-katani
afilu nisgarshu kegon de-havah lehu ketata. I thought the opposite! If a
guy's in the middle of having a fight with his wife, there's
marital stress, then we could say, 'All right, he's planning on to
do to marry this other woman, he's planning on the divorce.' No,
רש״י Rashi says that's the case that it's okay. Why is it
okay? Because רש״י Rashi says, I know, what do you mean? So
he says, דאכתי לא נתן דעתו מקמי הכי. De-achti lo natan da'ato
mikamei hachi. He says, oh, because if they were fighting before he
delivered the גט, get, then his plan to divorce his wife was
not in response to this woman.
Okay, so he would have
divorced his wife anyway.
Yeah, but... but no, but who cares?
If he was in a state where he was ready to divorce
his wife for whatever reason, so maybe he was manipulating this woman's
גט. get. It doesn't mean that the wife's divorce has to be
in reaction and started—the idea came out about this woman. He was
already planning or thinking about divorcing, and then this woman shows up
that he can manipulate a גט get with. No, that wasn't a
manipulation, he was going to get divorced whether or not this woman
was going to show up. Right, which is why we
shouldn't let him marry this woman! Exactly! No, but רש״י Rashi says
we do let him marry the woman!
No, you should let him marry the woman because—wait a second, he's
got a terrible marriage anyway, whether this woman was going to
show up or not he's going to divorce. Right.
Give her someone to marry.
No, he would have given
his wife the divorce anyway. Yeah, but that's a reason to think
that he faked the גט get of this woman. You don't say
it that way. Well, you can defend רש״י, Rashi, okay? That's what
רש״י Rashi says. Okay, and now if they
weren't fighting beforehand, then we say clearly it was all the result
of this woman.
He saw this woman, he wanted to marry her.
He faked her גט Get and then he decided to divorce his
wife and it all came as a result of the woman, but
if it started before this other woman showed up, then we're not
so suspicious. All right. איבעית אימא, איבעית אימא, הא דהוי תיגרא, הא
דלא הוי תיגרא. Iba'it eima, iba'it eima, ha de-havei tigra, ha de-lo
havei tigra. They were not fighting in either case. Okay, לא קשיא,
הא דארגיל הוא והא דארגילה היא. lo kashya, ha de-argil hu ve-ha
de-argilah hee. Who was the one that was pushing for divorce? If
he was the one that was pushing for
divorce, he can't remarry the woman. If she was the one pushing
for divorce, then we say all right, then he was obviously doing
nothing wrong and because he wanted to stay married to his wife.
So then we don't suspect the delivery of the גט. Get. Of
course, as the גמרא Gemara says
elsewhere, the way sort of interpersonal dynamics works, the marriage works is
you can sort of get your partner to try to want to
get a divorce. So, all right, anyway, let's take a look now
as the גמרא Gemara continues. וכולן שנישאו. Ve-khulan she-nisu. Now all, if
these women married another man, then they can go and marry the
first guy, the guy who delivered the גט Get and etc. קסלקא
דעתך מיתה אמיטה וגירושין אגירושין. Kasalka daitakh mita a-mita ve-geirushin a-geirushin. We
assumed it meant that there are two cases in the משנה. Mishna.
One is you testify the husband died, and the other is you
testify that you bring a גט. Get. And then they go ahead
and they marry another person and this other guy either dies or
divorces them. So the גמרא Gemara says we were assuming that when
you testify the husband died, then she remarried a second guy, the
second guy died. Or when you brought a גט, Get, she married
a second guy, the second guy divorced her. Just for parallel. So
the גמרא Gemara says but that raises interesting questions, which is: נימא
מתניתין דלא כרבי. Neima matnitin de-lo ke-Rabbi. This makes it not like
רבי. Rabbi. דאי כרבי אמר בתרי זימני הוי חזקה. De-ee ke-Rabbi amar
bi-trei zimnei havei khazaka. Another interesting discussion we're going to have later
in יבמות. Yevamot. A woman whose two husbands died on her sequentially.
So she was married twice and both husbands died. Are you allowed
to marry this woman? Do we say that twice already is a
type of a חזקה, khazaka, normally we say three but two maybe
is a type of a חזקה khazaka that we say, maybe there's
some reason why her husbands keep on dying on her and therefore
what, like a black widow or whatever? What, there was a woman
whose husbands kept dying on her, would you be third in line?
Well, but you want to.
So anyway, all right. So רבי Rabbi says don't remarry. So maybe
this משנה Mishna is saying you can remarry because that's the scenario.
So the גמרא Gemara says: לא, מיתה אגירושין וגירושין אמיתה. Lo, mita
a-geirushin ve-geirushin a-mita. We could say it was a mix and match.
The case where he testified the husband died, then the second husband
divorced her. Or the case where the husband divorced her, the second
husband died on her. All right, we'll worry enough about that later
on when we get to the discussion of רבי. Rabbi. Okay, וכולן
מותרות לבניהן ולאחיהם. Ve-khulan mutarot li-vneihen u-le-akheihem. And all these women can
marry the brother or the sons of the people who, whatever, brought
the גט Get and said their husband died. So the גמרא Gemara
says: מאי שנא מהא דתנן, דתניא. Mai shna mei-ha di-tnan, di-tanya. How
is it, or what's the difference than we taught in the ברייתא?
Beraita? הנידון מן האישה, Ha-nidon min ha-isha, if somebody is suspected of
having an affair with a woman. אסור באמה ובבתה. Asur be-imah u-ve-vitah.
You're not allowed to marry
the mother or the daughter. Why? Because if it was true that
you had an affair with that woman,
and then you marry the mother or the daughter, then you have
slept with a woman and her daughter, which is עריות arayot in
the תורה. Torah. Okay, ובאחותה, U-ve-akhota, and her sister. So you see
there that we, once there's a suspicion, so we extend it. So
here too we say that, you know, that made, now what exactly
is the exact point? It's not exactly clear. Because here it started
with a suspicion you did something wrong. So the issue really seems
to be, I think רש"י Rashi says it, let me see the
רש"י. Rashi. Okay, yeah, so it's important to understand this sequence because
remember the הלכה, halakha, the איסור issur of marrying or of sleeping
with is not just a woman and her daughter. It's your wife
and her daughter. Okay, or your wife, the sister of your wife.
So if you take a look at רש"י, Rashi, look at רש"י:
Rashi: אסור באמה ובבתה ובאחותה. Asur be-imah u-ve-vitah u-ve-akhota. The second wide
line. כדמפרש טעמא לקמן Ke-di-mefaresh ta'ama lekaman שמא לאחר, shema le-akhar, that's
my weird bell I have, oh gosh, I don't even know what's
going on here. Okay. שמא לאחר כדמפרש טעמא לקמן שמא לאחר שישא
אמה או בתה תזנה זו עמו. Ke-di-mefaresh ta'ama lekaman shema le-akhar she-yisa
imah o bitah tizneh zo imo. Okay, the real concern is not
that you already had sex with this woman and now you're married
to her mother or daughter. The point is you cannot be married
to a woman and then have sex with her mother or daughter.
But it only starts once you're married to the woman. Okay? Is
that clear? You have to first be married to a woman, now
you're married to the woman, don't have sex with her mother or
with her daughter. So the fact that you had sex beforehand to
a woman who wasn't your wife does not prohibit you as far
as marrying or having sex with her mother at another time. Right.
So, okay, let's take a look. כדמפרש טעמא לקמן שמא לאחר שישא
אמה או בתה תזנה זו עמו. Ke-di-mefaresh ta'ama lekaman shema le-akhar she-yisa
imah o bitah tizneh zo imo. ובזנות קמא לא. U-vi-znut kamma lo.
Okay, so let's take a look. ומפרש Umfareish בגמרא Bag'mara דנאמר De'ne'emar
שלאחר She'le'achar שזנה She'zana עם Im הבת Ha'bat אינה Eina נאסרת Ne'eseret
עליו Alav אמו Imo ובזנות U'viznut קמא kama לא lo הוי havei
איסור issur באמו be'imo ובקרובותיה u'v'krovoteha וקיימא לן ve'kaima lan נושאין nosin
על al האנוסה ha'anusa ועל ve'al המפותה ha'meputa דלא de'lo נאסרו ne'esru
קרובות krovot אישה isha אלא ela לאיש l'ish אלא ela אם im
כן kein קירב keirav לה lah לראשונה larishona דאישות de'ishut כתיב ketiv
בה, bah, okay? So therefore it's only once you're married. So whether
or not the concern is not that now that you're marrying mother
or daughter or sister that's going to be an איסור. issur. The
concern is you're marrying mother or daughter or sister and you figure
hey I had got now I got an idea I'll marry her
mother and then when the daughter comes over for a visit I'll
be able to continue my affair with the daughter. So the reason
we don't allow when there's a suspicion of this affair to marry
mother or daughter or sister is because we're afraid that then because
family stays together you'll have opportunity and you'll do it once it
really becomes an איסור עריות issur arayos and it will lead to
it. Okay so here too the גמרא G'mara saying I get that
we're not afraid you're going to sin just so your brother can
marry this woman. But maybe you're sinning for your own sake. You're
going to lie about this גט, get, have your brother marry her,
so that's a nice sort of make it look all כשר kosher
so nobody will suspect you. And then when you go to visit
your brother you'll find opportunity to sleep with this woman. So why
don't we have the same type of a concern? So let's take
a look. The גמרא G'mara says נשי לגבי נשי שכיחן דאזלן, nashi
l'gabei nashi sh'kichan de'azlan, גברי לגבי גברי לא שכיחן. gavri l'gabei gavri
lo sh'kichan. So the גמרא G'mara says you know women in the
family spend more time together. Mother and sister and daughter so they
visit each other. Right, they visit each other. So if you're married
to one woman you'll have opportunity to have some encounter with the
mother or the sister or the daughter. But you know brothers don't
spend so much time don't visit each other so much. So if
your brother is married to a woman that you're interested in you
won't have so much opportunity with her. All right, אי נמי, i
nami, the גמרא G'mara says, or you could say נשי דלא אסרן
שכיבתן אהדדי לא קפדי אהדדי, nashi d'lo asran sh'chivatan ahadadi lo kapdi
ahadadi, גברי דאסרן שכיבתן אהדדי קפדי אהדדי. gavri d'asran sh'chivatan ahadadi kapdi
ahadadi. Another fascinating answer which it says if it were true that
if you actually slept with your wife's sister, okay, that would actually
not make you forbidden to continue living with your wife. So therefore
she's not so מקפיד makpid if maybe you'll wind up sleeping with
her sister or her daughter because it's not actually going to affect
her marriage הלכתית. halachitit. But if your brother's wife if you're interested
in her he's pretty מקפיד makpid because if you wind up sleeping
with her then she's forbidden on him and then they'll have to
get a divorce. Again quite fascinating like really? That's the level of
difference here? Okay, אי נמי, i nami, or you could say אי
הכי, i hachi, the גמרא G'mara says, אביו נמי. aviv nami. If
that's true then why don't we even allow the father to marry
this woman that you brought the גט get for? Why does it
only say brother and son? So the גמרא G'mara wants these are
not types of concerns when a male relative is married to these
women. גמרא G'mara says you're right, לא מיבעיא קאמר, lo mibaya ka'amar,
לא מיבעיא אביו, lo mibaya aviv, clearly the father could marry this
woman דבז בניה מיניה d'baz b'nei minei that the father that the
son is embarrassed to try to have an affair with his father's
wife. Again somebody before was mentioning יהודה ותמר Yehuda v'Tamar you could
also think about ראובן Reuven and יעקב's Yaakov אשת איש. eshet ish.
Exactly. אבל בנו דלא בז אביו מיניה aval b'no d'lo baz aviv
minei but a son's wife that a father might not feel embarrassed
because it's his son he feels he can take advantage. אימא לא,
eima lo, maybe we
won't allow it. קמשמע לן ka'mashma lan that we
do. So quite fascinating the idea here the concern is not some
you're sinning for the sake of somebody else. You'll only sin for
yourself but you want a relative to marry so that you'll have
an opportunity to have an affair. Okay and the fascinating just distinctions
between men and women in this regard which don't seem to be
like probably you know factually true but at least the גמרא G'mara
sort of teases as theoretical distinctions. Okay. הדרן עלך המביא גט באשת
אחיו. Hadran alach hameivi get b'eshet achiv. Let's see if we can
get to at least the bottom of the דף daf and if
you the עמוד ב amud bet is very small so maybe at
least tomorrow we'll catch up. I keep on saying that. But let's
go for it. ארבעה אחים, arba'ah achim, this should be familiar to
you. ארבעה אחים arba'ah achim שנים מהם נושאים שתי אחיות. shnayim mehem
nosim shtei achayot. So ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon are married to
רחל Rachel and לאה, Leah, sisters. ומתו הנסואות האחיות u'metu ha'nisuot ha'achayot
and ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon die. הרי אלו חולצות ולא מתייבמות.
harei elu chulot v'lo mityabmot. So now you've got לוי Levi and
יהודה. Yehuda. So they we've done this multiple times, a משנה mishna
we've already seen many times. Okay but you can't see it too
many times. You have ראובן Reuven and שמעון, Shimon, לוי Levi and
יהודה. Yehuda. Okay ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon are married to רחל
Rachel and לאה, Leah, sisters. They both die. Okay. לוי Levi cannot
do יבום Yibbum with רחל Rachel because רחל Rachel is, anybody? Anybody?
אחות זקוקתו, Achot Zekukaso, right? There's זיקה zika both ways. So and
same with יהודה Yehuda so they can't do it. So all they
can do is חליצה. chalitza. Now after he's done חליצה chalitza with
רחל, Rachel, why not go ahead and then do... יבום Yibbum with
לאה, Leah, לאה Leah is no longer אחות זקוקתו, Achot Zekukaso רחל
Rachel is no longer זיקה Zika because לאה, Leah, if she's not
going to be אחות זקוקתו, Achot Zekukaso, becomes אחות חלוצתו. Achot Chaluzaso.
Okay.
So either there's a זיקה Zika here and if he gets rid
of the זיקה, Zika, it's a חליצה. Chalizah.
And either way, זיקה Zika is quasi marriage, חליצה Chalizah is quasi
divorce, so he can't do יבום Yibbum, with לאה Leah cause he's
either having sex with the woman he's quasi married with, with the
sister of the woman he's either quasi married to or quasi divorced
from. Okay. And the same is true with יהודה. Yehuda. Okay. So
they each have to do חליצה Chalizah to the both... so חליצה
Chalizah has to be done. They don't each have to do it,
but anyway, the women require you do חליצה Chalizah with the women.
Is it a דאורייתא? d'Oraisa? No, no, אחות חלוצתו Achot Chaluzaso is
certainly דרבנן, d'Rabbanan, אחות זקוקתו Achot Zekukaso, a little bit vaguer. All
right. So anyway, הרי אלו חולצות ולא מתייבמות. Harei Elu Chotzos V'lo
Misyabmos. אם קדמו וכנסו, Im Kadmu V'kinsu, similar to the theme before
which we had, you know, digressed from, if they actually went ahead
and went through with it, יוציאו. Yotziu. They have to get divorced
because that was a real issue of if he went ahead and
he had יבום, Yibbum there was a real issue about אחות זקוקתו,
Achot Zekukaso, you know? And if the אחות זקוקתו, Achot Zekukaso. by
the way, is a דאורייתא d'Oraisa problem and then she's really דאורייתא
d'Oraisa not able to marry her, that actually makes it worse, that
makes it אשת אחיו, Eshes Achiv, that makes it an ערוה דאורייתא.
Ervah d'Oraisa. Okay, so they have to get divorced. רבי אליעזר אומר,
Rabbi Eliezer Omer, בית שמאי אומרים יקיים. Beis Shammai Omrim Yekayem. בית
שמאי Beis Shammai actually says no, בדיעבד, b'dieved, maybe it was only
a דרבנן d'Rabbanan problem, בדיעבד b'dieved you can keep the marriage. ובית
הלל אומרים יוציאו. U'Beis Hillel Omrim Yotziu. Okay. היתה אחת מהן אסורה
עליו Haysa Achas Min Ha'asura Lav על האחד איסור ערוה, Al Ha'echad
Issur Ervah, אסור בה ומותר באחותה. Assur Bah U'muttar Bachotah. If רחל
Rachel was לוי's Levi sister, then רחל Rachel is not זקוקתו. Zekukaso.
So then he's free to do יבום Yibbum with לאה. Leah. Then
רחל Rachel gets out of the picture. Okay. איסור ערוה, Issur Ervah,
okay. Now, והשניה אסורה בשניהן. V'hashenia Assura Besheihen. But for יהודה, Yehuda,
they're both, he, both of them are זקוקתו, Zekukaso, neither of them
is an ערוה Ervah to him, so he still has to... he
cannot do יבום Yibbum with either. איסור מצוה ואיסור קדושה, Issur Mitzvah
V'Issur Kedusha, let's say רחל Rachel was אסור assur to לוי, Levi,
not as his... it wasn't his daughter, but let's say it was
like an איסור דרבנן, Issur d'Rabbanan, right? One of those שניות, Shniyos,
or it was like a, you know, case of, I don't know,
some איסור Issur like a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and an אלמנה
Almana or something. Okay? So in that case, that case is not
strong enough, certainly not the דרבנן, d'Rabbanan, but even just the איסור
לאו, Issur Lav, if it's not a real ערוה, Ervah, is not
enough to remove זיקה. Zika. So even though he cannot consummate with
רחל Rachel for these additional reasons, she still remains זקוקתו. Zekukaso. So
היתה אחת מהן אסורה עליו, Haysa Achas Min Ha'asura Lav, איסור מצוה
ואיסור קדושה, Issur Mitzvah V'Issur Kedusha, חולצת ולא מתייבמת. Choletzes V'lo Misyabemes.
Then he has to do חליצה Chalizah with her. The only thing
that removes the זיקה Zika from רחל Rachel is a real איסור
ערוה. Issur Ervah. היתה אחת מהן אסורה על זה איסור ערוה והשניה
אסורה על זה איסור ערוה, Haysa Achas Min Ha'asura Al Zeh Issur
Ervah V'hashenia Assura Al Zeh Issur Ervah, רחל Rachel is לוי's Levi
daughter, לאה Leah is יהודה's Yehuda daughter. So in that type of
a case, right? So if רחל Rachel is לוי's Levi daughter, רחל's
Rachel out of the picture for לוי, Levi, he can do יבום
Yibbum with לאה. Leah. And if לאה Leah is יהודה's Yehuda daughter,
she's out of the picture for יהודה, Yehuda, frees him to do
יבום Yibbum. with רחל. Rachel. So לוי Levi and שמעון Shimon married
their nieces. Yeah. אסורה לזה מותרת לזה ואסורה לזה מותרת לזה. Assura
L'zeh Muteres L'zeh V'assura L'zeh Muteres L'zeh. The one that's forbidden to
one is permissible to the other and vice versa. וזו היא שאמרו,
V'zu Hi She'amru, and this is what they said, אחותה כשהיא יבמתה,
Achosa K'sheyevimta, if you have an ערוה Ervah that is... that's the
woman here. רחל Rachel is לאה's Leah sister and her sister-in-law, right?
That's this case. Sister and sister-in-law. אחותה כשהיא יבמתה, Achosa K'sheyevimta, if
one of them is an ערוה, Ervah, then the הלכה Halacha is
או חולצת או מתייבמת. O Choletzes O Misyabemes. So the one who
is the sister of the ערוה Ervah can either have חליצה Chalizah
or יבום. Yibbum. If one of them is an ערוה, Ervah, she's
out of the picture, and the sister sister-in-law can do חליצה Chalizah
or יבום. Yibbum Just read a line in the גמרא, Gemara, שמע
מינה יש זיקה דאי אין זיקה מכדי. Shma Mina Yesh Zika D'ein
Zika Michtei. Obviously it's a problem of זיקה, Zika, אחות זקוקתו, because
if not, let's take a look. הני מתרי בתי קאתו, Hani MiTrei
Battei Kasin, they're coming from two separate households, right? So it's not
a צרה Tzara case. So האי ייבם חדא והאי ייבם חדא. Hai
Yavem Chada V'Hai Yavem Chada. Why doesn't ראובן Reuven do יבום Yibbum
with... not ראובן, Reuven, לוי Levi with one and יהודה Yehuda with
the other? The only problem here, as we've been describing, is this
idea of אחות זקוקתו. So the גמרא Gemara says, so you see
that's what's going on. So the גמרא Gemara says no, לעולם אימא
לך אין זיקה. L'olam Eima Lach Ein Zika. So what's the problem?
משום דקסבר אסור לבטל מצות יבם. Mishum Dekasavar Assur L'vattel Mitzvas Yabum.
So now we've seen that there's a very far-fetched explanation, let's just
read it again. דעד מייבם חד מיית אידך. D'ad Meyabem Chad Meyis
Idach. Not really, there's no idea of זיקה. Zika. לוי Levi really
could do יבום Yibbum with רחל. Rachel. Okay? He says the connection
with לאה Leah is insignificant. But what's going to happen? While לאה
Leah now is... he can't do it with both רחל Rachel and
לאה, Leah, they're sisters. So לאה Leah has to wait for יבום
Yibbum or חליצה Chalizah with יהודה. Yehuda. While she's waiting, יהודה Yehuda
dies. So it caused, and that would be a case that he
was some, either יבום yibum or some—either יבום yibum or חליצה chalitza
was necessary and the circumstances didn't allow it. But if לוי Levi
does חליצה chalitza with רחל, Rachel, then even if יהודה Yehuda dies,
he can go ahead and do חליצה chalitza with לאה. Leah. So
we don't allow יבום yibum because it'll limit—it might lead to a
case where לאה Leah doesn't wind up getting יבום yibum or חליצה.
chalitza. Very far-fetched explanation. Let's just read it and we'll end with
that for today. אדייבין חד מית אידך ad yabin chad mit idach
while לוי Levi does יבום yibum with one, then the other, יהודה,
Yehuda, would die, וקמבטל מצות יבמין vekamavatel mitzvas yabmin and then the
מצוה mitzvah of יבום would fall by the wayside. Okay, so we
will pick up with this משנה. mishnah.